Let's take a look at Task 18.
This one is a bit tricky since it
requires additional knowledge about
infinite sets, how to enumerate them, and
then find a way to define this in Haskell.
Okay, so what's the task?
We should give definitions for these
three lists 'ints', 'pairs', and 'triples'
and 'ints' should be the set, or
the list, of all integer numbers.
That is all the natural numbers
and the negative whole numbers.
And then we should define the set
of all pairs of natural numbers
and finally the set of all triples of two
natural numbers and one integer number.
Okay, so let's start with the integers.
Abstractly, what we would like to
define is something like starting with 0
then we take all the natural numbers
and then something like this.
We say, okay, we have a list comprehension or
a list containing all the negative numbers so
we would have all the positive numbers
and 0 and then all the negative numbers.
But of course, this does not work because
there are infinitely many positive numbers, so
this results basically in us saying, okay, we're
starting with 0, then there's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, etc.
So there are all these infinitely many numbers
but we never actually get to the -1 part.
So there are elements missing.
And now we need a clever way to
enumerate all these elements such that we
can actually encounter them in the list.
For integers, this is not too tricky
if you think about it for a second.
You just start with 0, then you go to 1, and then
to -1, then to -2, and 2, or the other way around.
You could also do -1 here and then 1.
And then you go on, and this way
each of these numbers is enumerated.
And now the question is how do we
encode this in terms of Haskell syntax?
Okay, so let's start with a list comprehension;
seems like a good starting point.
So we want to have these values
and then from where to where?
Hmm, okay, so this is a bit
tricky to write, it seems.
There's a
small function that we can use from the prelude
that is called concat that is really helpful here.
So we switch over to ghci.
concat of a list of lists flattens the list.
So if you, for example, have a list
[1, 2] and [3, 4], something like that,
then concat [[1, 2], [3, 4]] will give
us the list without the nesting of lists.
We can use this here to take n and
-n and then let n range from 1 to
infinity ... or just keep going.
Now obviously there's a type error here because
this is not a list of Integers
but a list of lists of Integers.
And now we use concat to flatten this list.
Okay, let's load this into ghci and take a look.
So we use take and then some number
like 20, or something like that,
because obviously this is an infinite list
and we cannot print out all the elements.
So now we have this list where we
have 1, -1, 2, -2, 3, -3, and so on.
Only the 0 is missing.
So what we can do is, we can just
add it to the front of the list.
We could also just start with 0 here.
If we do that, then we have two 0's, obviously,
since we have 0 here and -0 is still 0.
And the task requires that we
don't have any duplicate elements.
You can just fix this by saying, okay, just take
the tail; drop the first element of this list.
If we now take a look at this list,
we have exactly what we sketched
out here; what we wanted to define.
Alright, so that's a list of all integers.
Now the list of all pairs of natural numbers:
Again, let's start with a list comprehension
and we want some pairs x and y.
And our first approach might be to say, natural
numbers, okay, these are basically these.
Let's just try it this way, right.
Take all the natural numbers into x and then all
the natural numbers into y and build all pairs.
This is how list comprehensions work, right?
This probably is what we want.
Well, let's take a look.
Okay, so now we're getting
(0,0), (0,1), (0,2), (0,3).
So the first element always stays 0, and then
we enumerate all the other natural numbers.
But that's a problem because we will
never arrive at 1 in the first component
because there is an infinite amount of natural
numbers that we can have in the second component.
Okay, so this is where it becomes a bit tricky
because you have to think about how to actually
enumerate these in a way such that you
pass each combination, so to speak.
So that everything occurs in the list.
Okay, so what's the trick?
There's something called diagonalization where if
you would plot these pairs, you want to enumerate
in a two-dimensional table, you would make
a diagonal movement through this table.
It's not really that important to understand
here, but the key observation is that on such a
diagonal in this traversal scheme, the components
have a constant sum on each of these diagonals.
So the trick is to print out or to generate first
all pairs with components that sum up to 0,
then all pairs with components that sum up to 1,
which is (0, 1) and (1, 0),
and then for 2 and so on.
So we would have (0, 2) then (1, 1)
and then (2, 0) and so on.
And for each of these
constant 0, 1, 2, and so on, there's only a
finite number of these combinations, right.
So each pair necessarily has a sum of its
two components, and if we enumerate all these
lists of pairs with a constant sum, we will
eventually enumerate all components, right.
So the trick here is to say x + y
has to be equal to some, let's call it c for
constant, and this constant moves from 0 upwards.
For the same reason, the other version didn't
work; this will also not work this way because
we're still taking all the
combinations of x and y here.
And so the list hangs after the first element
because we are now trying to find an element with
components that sum up to 0 in all
these tuples we've created so far.
So we need a slightly different
approach that doesn't have infinite
lists for x and y to draw from.
The straightforward way would be to say, if we
want x and y to sum up to c, then obviously x
cannot be greater than c, same for y and even
more precisely y cannot be greater than c-x.
Okay, now we get some pairs, and these
are exactly what we sketched out here.
So we start with (0,0) so
all the pairs that sum up to
0, then we have all the pairs that sum up to
1, then 2, 3, 4 and the first of the 5-pairs.
Okay, this works, but we can realize that
we're still doing a bit of extra work here.
Because if we look at it; well let's take
this constraint here into consideration;
we say that x goes from 0 to c and y goes from 0
to c - x, and we want to check that x + y = c.
Well, if we carefully look at this we see that
y actually fulfills this only for c-x, right.
So we don't need to draw y from a range and have
this condition, we can directly compute y as c-x.
Okay, let's check this again - that we didn't
break anything - so we still have the 0s, the 1s,
the 2s, the 3s, and so on,
so this still works, okay.
Very good. Now this is
where it gets really tricky.
We really have to think about
it quite a bit but once you get
the idea it's actually pretty straightforward.
Let's try to figure it out.
So we should give the set of all triples of
two natural numbers and an integer number.
There's no straightforward way to actually
enumerate these that immediately
comes to mind but if we would write a
comprehension that magically works, kind of, we
would probably want to write something like this:
(x, y, z) and x and y are taken out
of the 'pairs' list and z is taken
out of the integers ('Ints') because we have
enumerated all the integers and all the pairs.
And what we would like to do is combine
this in a way that this actually works.
In the finite case, if 'pairs' and 'Ints' were
finite, this would actually do the right thing.
But since they are infinite we have to make
sure that we reach every element at some point.
Okay, because we look
for 'triples' we have the same problem as with
'pairs'; we always start with the (0,0,_) tuple and
then enumerate all the integers which means we
never get into the (0,1,_) tuple from the list.
Okay, so what's the
observation you can make here?
You can try to figure out some way like
you did here with the sum to actually
enumerate them all together
as a one single expression.
But there's another observation you can make.
We have this set of pairs, right?
And this set of pairs contains all
the combinations of natural numbers,
every single combination there is.
And we have two lists 'pairs'
and 'Ints', and we want to have
all the combinations of
elements of these two lists.
So if we take the 'pairs' list as
a way to produce all the different
possibilities how to index two lists, if we
look at it that way we can see that we have to
combine the 0th element of one list with the
0th element of the second list and so on.
Take element 0 from the first list
and element 1 from the second list,
element 1 from the first list and element
0 from the second list, then element 0 from
the first list and element 2
from the second list and so on.
And by doing this along this scheme,
with these pairs we will eventually
reach every combination exactly once.
And this is why the task states
that you are allowed to use the
list indexing operator (!!) here
because it makes it really easy.
Because all you have to do is say, I'm
getting indices i and j from 'pairs' and then
we take that element.
So (x,y) is the 'pairs' list and index i, and
z is the integer list at index j.
Okay, so now there's a type error here because
the indexing function expects us to use
Ints but we have Integers here, so we need one
conversion fromIntegral and fromIntegral here.
Okay, let's change the layout
so that it's easier to read.
These brackets are redundant. Let's remove them.
Okay, let's load this up and take
a look at the first 20 triples.
Well, we start with a triple of all zeros,
then we have (0,0,1), (0,1,0), (0,0,-1).
You can already see that this is quite
complicated to actually figure out
a nice pattern here like we
did with our constant sum.
But by carefully thinking
about it, we see that if we
actually take every combination of possible
indexing from this pair and then use
these indices to index 'pairs' and 'Ints', then
we will actually enumerate all of these triples.
Okay, that's basically the task.
Once you've understood how to actually do
this last part, it might seem quite easy.
But actually coming up with this idea
is not necessarily straightforward.
If you're not used to thinking about these things
a lot, which is why this was an optional task
that is quite difficult.